We're going to get started.
我们马上开始上课
Handouts are the by the door if anybody didn't pick one up.
如果谁还没拿到讲义的话请在门口领取
My name is Charles Leiserson.
我叫Charles Leiserson
I will be lecturing this course this term, Introduction to Algorithms,
这学期将由我来执教这门课，算法导论
with Erik Demaine.
和我一起执教的是Erik Demaine
In addition, this is an SMA course, a Singapore MIT Alliance course
另外，这是一门SMA课程，即新加坡-MIT联盟课程
which will be run in Singapore by David Hsu.
将由David Hsu提供给新加坡
And so all the lectures will be videotaped
所有的课程将被录像
and made available on the Web for the Singapore students,
并且通过网络提供给新加坡的学生
as well as for MIT students who choose to watch them on the Web.
MIT的学生也可以在网上选择观看
If you have an issue of not wanting to be on the videotape,
如果你不想上镜头
you should sit in the back row.
你就坐到后排去
OK? Otherwise, you will be on it.
好吗？否则，你就会出现在镜头里
There is a video recording policy, but it seems like they ran out.
有个关于录像的条款，但貌似已经发完了
If anybody wants to see it,
如果谁想看下这个条款
people, if they could just sort of pass them around maybe a little bit,
同学们，你们互相借阅下
once you're done reading it, or you can come up.
还没看到的可以来我这里
I did secure one copy.
我这里还留有一份
Before we get into the content of the course,
在我们开始这门课之前
let's briefly go over the course information
先概括下这门课的全貌
because there are some administrative things that we sort of have to do.
因为这门课有一些规定我们得简单的说下
As you can see, this term we have a big staff.
如你所见，这学期我们有很多助教
Take a look at the handout here.
看看讲义这里
Including this term six TAs,
共有六个助教
which is two more TAs than we normally get for this course.
这比我们以前在这门课中的助教多了2名
That means recitations will be particularly small.
这就是说复习课能够做到十分小班化
There is a World Wide Web page,
我们做了个网站
and you should bookmark that and go there regularly
你应该把它加入收藏并且经常访问它
because that is where everything will be distributed.
因为这门课的所有相关信息都在那里发布
Email.
邮箱
You should not be emailing directly to,
你们不要直接发邮件给个人
even though we give you our email addresses,
即便我们给了你们邮件地址
to the individual members of the staff.
也不要直接发给某一名教职人员
You should email us generally.
你应该发邮件给到我们全体
And the reason is you will get much faster response.
原因是你可以得到更迅速的回复
And also, for any communications,
此外，对于任何的沟通
generally we like to monitor what the communications are
我们通常都想查看完整的来往记录
so it's helpful to have emails coming to everybody on the course staff.
所以把电子邮件群发给课程相关的所有工作人员是有益的
As I mentioned, we will be doing distance learning this term.
正如我前面提到的，我们本学期将进行远程教学
And so you can watch lectures online if you choose to do that.
所以你想的话，可以观看在线课程
I would recommend, for people who have the opportunity to watch, to come live.
我建议，有机会在线观看的同学，应该到现场看看
It's better live. You get to interact.
在现场效果更好，你可以进行交互
There's an intangible that comes with having it live.
到现场来的话会有无形的收益
In fact, in addition to the videos,
事实上，除了视频之外
I meet weekly with the Singapore students
我每周会和新加坡的学生有面对面交流
so that they have a live session as well.
所以他们也会有现场讨论的契机
Prerequisites.
预备知识
The prerequisites for this course are 6.042,
（算法导论）这门课的预备知识是6.042
which is Math for Computer Science, and 6.001.
也就是计算科学的数学基础，以及6.001
You basically need discrete mathematics and probability,
你还要懂离散数学和概率论的基础知识
as well as programming experience to take this course successfully.
以及编程经验，有了这些你才能学好这门课
People do not have that background should not be in the class.
没有上过这些基础课的同学是不能上这门课的
We will be checking prerequisites.
我们会检查预备知识
If you have any questions, please come to talk to us after class.
如果你有任何问题，请在课后告诉我们
Let's see. Lectures are here.
嗯，课是在这里上的
For SMA students,
对于SMA的学生
they have the videotapes and they will also have a weekly meeting.
他们有课程的视频以及每周的讨论例会
Students must attend a one-hour recitation session each week.
同学们必须每周参加一个小时的复习课
There will be new material presented in the recitation.
在复习课上会发一些新的资料
Unlike the lectures, they will not be online.
与现场课程不同的是，这些不会放到网上
Unlike the lectures,
还有
there will not be lecture notes distributed for the recitations in general.
在复习课上通常不会分发课程讲义
And, yet, there will be material there that is directly on the exams.
还有，有些内容就是考试直接会考的
And so every term we say oh, when did you cover that?
每学期末都有人会说，这个什么时候讲过？
That was in recitation. You missed that one.
复习课讲过，你缺勤了吧
So, recitations are mandatory.
所以，复习课是一定要上的
And, in particular, also let me just mention
尤其是，我要指出
your recitation instructor is the one who assigns your final grade.
你复习课导师就是决定你最终成绩的人
So we have a grade meeting and keep everybody normal,
所以我们有一个分数评委会来保证所有人的成绩都是公平的
but your recitation has the final say on your grade.
但是你的复习课导师会最终决定你的成绩
Handouts.
讲义
Handouts are available on the course Web page.
讲义可以从课程主页上得到
We will not generally, except for this one, first handout,
除了第一份讲义，我们一般不会
be bringing handouts to class.
把讲义带到课堂上
Textbook is this book, Introduction to Algorithms.
课本是这本书，《算法导论》
MIT students can get it any of the local bookstores, including the MIT Coop.
附近任何一个书店都能买到它，包括MIT Coop
There is also a new online service that provides textbooks.
还有新的在线服务也能提供这本书
You can also get a discount if you buy it at the MIT Press Bookstore.
如果你从MIT出版社书店购买可以的获得一个折扣
There is a coupon in the MIT Student Telephone Directory
在MIT学生电话目录里有个优惠券
for a discount on MIT Press books.
在MIT出版社书店可以打折
And you can use that to purchase this book at a discount.
你可以使用优惠券购买这本书
Course website. This is the course website.
课程网站 这里是课程网站
It links to the Stellar website, which is where, actually, everything will be kept.
它连到Stellar网站，这个网站会把一切保存下来
And SMA students have their own website.
SMA学生有自己的网站
Some students find this course particularly challenging
一些学生发现这门课非常具有挑战性
so we will have extra help.
所以我们会有额外的帮助
We will post weekly office hours on the course website for the TAs.
我们会在课程网站上贴出助教的每周工作时段
And then as an experiment this term,
然后作为本学期的一个试验
we are going to offer homework labs for this class.
我们会为这个班提供课外作业实验室
What a homework lab is,
所谓课外作业实验室
is it's a place and a time you can go
就是在规定时间你可以去一个地方
where other people in the course will go to do homework.
那里有其他学习这门课的同学会在那里做课后作业
And there will be typically two TAs who staff the lab.
而且那儿会安排两个实验室助教
And so, as you're working on your homework,
所以，如果你在那里做课后作业
you can get help from the TAs if you need it.
你可以在需要的情况下获得助教的帮助
And it's generally a place, we're going to schedule those,
这将成为一个常规方，我们会安排的
and they will be on the course calendar
安排会写在课程日程表上
for where it is and when it is that they will be held,
时间和地点都会清楚地列出来
but usually Sundays 2:00 to 4:00 pm, or else it will be some evening.
通常是星期天的下午2点到4点，或者会是某个晚上
I think the first one is an evening, right?
我想把第一次（课外作业实验室）放到晚上，好么？
Near to when the homework is due.
大概就在交作业的前夕
Your best bet is try to do the homework in advance of the homework lab.
你最好在去课外作业实验室之前就试着自己做作业
But then, if you want extra help,
只有这样，才会有额外的帮助
if you want to talk over your solutions with people
才会有东西拿来和别人讨论
because as we will talk about problem sets
关于作业，待会我会讲到
you can solve in collaboration with other people in the class.
和本班同学合作解决问题是允许的
In addition, there are several peer assistance programs.
另外，这里还有数个学生互助项目
Also the Office of Minority Education has an assistance program,
另外少数民族教育办公室也有一套协助计划
and those usually get booked up pretty quickly.
一般这些很快会被预订完
If you're interested in those,
如果你有兴趣
good idea to make an appointment to get there and get help soon.
一个好的做法就是提前预约，才能得到帮助
The homework labs, I hope a lot of people will try that out.
我希望大家都能去参加这个课后作业实验室
We've never done this. I don't know of any other course.
我们从来没有这样做过，我也不知道其他课程是否这样做
Do other people know of courses at MIT that have done this?
谁知道是否有其他的MIT课程在这样做？
6.011 did it, OK. Good.
6.011课程这样做过，了解了，好的
And was it successful in that class? Never went, OK.
在那个班开放的成功么？从来没去过，天
Good.
好吧
We will see.
走一步算一步
If it's not paying off
如果（我们的课后实验室）没有成功
then we will just return to ordinary office hours for those TAs,
那么我们的助教会回归平常的办公时间
but I think for some students that is a good opportunity.
但我认为对一些学生来说（实验室）是个很好的机会
If you wish to be registered in this course,
如果你想注册参加这个课程
you must sign up on the course Web page.
你必须在课程主页上注册
So, that is requirement one. It must be done today.
要求之一，今天必须完成这件事儿
You will find it difficult to pass the course if you are not in the class.
如果你缺勤，就很难通过考试
And you should notify your TA if you decide to drop
如果你决定放弃这门课，应该告诉你的助教
so that we can get you off and stop the mailings,
这样我们可以把你移出邮件列表
stop the spam.
省得你不断收到垃圾邮件
And you should register today before 7:00 PM.
你必须在晚上7点之前注册
And then we're going to email
那时我们会发送邮件
your recitation assignment to you before noon tomorrow.
在明天中午之前发出你们的复习课作业
And if you don't receive this information by Thursday Noon,
如果你在周四之前没有收到这封邮件
please send us an email to the course staff generally,
请群发一个邮件给课程的所有工作人员
not to me individually,
不要发给我个人
saying that you didn't receive your recitation assignment.
如果你没收到复习课作业的话
And so if you haven't received it by Thursday noon you want to.
在周四中午之前没有收到复习课作业，你就需要…
I think generally they are going to send them out tonight
我想复习课作业今晚就会发出
or at least by tomorrow morning. Yeah.
或者最迟明天早上，嗯
SMA students don't have to worry about this.
SMA的学生不用为此操心
Problem sets. We have nine problem sets
习题集，我们有九套习题集
that we project will be assigned during the semester.
会在这学期分发下去
A couple things about problem sets.
几件关于习题集的事
Homeworks won't generally be accepted,
作业迟交等现象
if you have extenuating circumstances
一般是不被允许的
you should make prior arrangements with your recitation instructor.
除非你事先和复习课导师沟通过
In fact, almost all of the administrative stuff,
事实上，几乎所有教务上的事
you shouldn't come to me to ask and say can I hand in something late?
都不应该跑来问我，说我可以迟一点交某某东西么？
You should be talking to your recitation instructor.
你应该告诉你的复习课导师
You can read the other things about the form,
你可以阅读下其他相关规定
but let me just mention that there are exercises that should be solved
我只提一下，还会有一些不用上交的练习
but not handed in as well to give you drill on the material.
但这部分练习同样有助于你深入理解知识
I highly recommend you doing the exercises.
我强烈推荐你们做这些练习题
They both test your understanding of the material,
作业和练习都可以帮你理解知识
and exercises have this way of finding themselves on quizzes.
考题里面可能会有练习题中的原题
You're often asked to describe algorithms.
你应该会被要求描述各种算法
And here is a little outline of what you can use to describe an algorithm.
而你想描述某种算法的话，这里有一个小的模板
The grading policy is something that somehow I cover.
评分办法是我一定会提到的
And always every term there are at least a couple of students
但每学期总是有少数几个学生说不知道
who pretend like I never showed them this.
就好像我没有讲过这些一样
If you skip problems it has a nonlinear effect on your grade.
如果作业中你跳过某些题，这会对成绩造成非线性的影响
Nonlinear, OK?
非线性，听清楚了？
If you don't skip any problems, no effect on your grade.
没有漏题，成绩将不会受到影响
If you skip one problem, a hundredth of a letter grade, we can handle that.
跳过任何一题，我们会扣除你1%个字母等的成绩
But two problems it's a tenth.
跳过两个题目就扣除1/10
And, as you see, by the time you have skipped like five-- letter grades,
如你所见，如果你跳过五道题
it is already a third, five problems.
将扣除1/3
This is not problem sets, by the way.
顺便说下，我说的不是习题集漏交次数
This is problems, OK? You're down a third of a letter grade.
我说的是跳过的题目数目，五个题将下降1/3字母等
And if you don't do nine or more,
如果你漏掉完成9道题或以上
so that's typically about three to four problem sets,
大概是三到四次习题集的内容
you don't pass the class.
你就不可能及格了
I always have some students coming at the end of the year
年末的时候经常有学生跑来找我
saying oh, I didn't do any of my problems.
说哦，我作业一道题也没写
Can you just pass me because I did OK on the exams?
我如果考试还可以的话，能让我及格吗？
Answer no, a very simple answer because we've said it upfront.
答案是不可能，一句话，我们有言在先
So, the problem sets are an integral part of the course.
所以习题集是这门课程不可分割的一部分
Collaboration policy.
合作规则
This is extremely important so everybody pay attention.
这是非常重要的，所以每个人都要注意
If you are asleep now wake up.
如果你在打瞌睡，现在醒醒
Like that's going to wake anybody up, right?
这样的事儿会让任何人清醒过来，对吧？
The goal of homework.
课后作业的目的
Professor Demaine and my philosophy is that
Demaine教授和我的观点是
the goal of homework is to help you learn the material.
家庭作业的目标是帮你学习这些知识
And one way of helping to learn is not to just be stuck and unable to solve something
促进学习的一个办法是不要卡在一道题目上
because then you're in no better shape when the exam roles around,
因为这对你考试的时候没有任何帮助
which is where we're actually evaluating you.
考试才是检验你真枪实弹水平的地方
So, you're encouraged to collaborate.
所以在做作业时你大可以和别人合作
But there are some commonsense things about collaboration.
但是有一些关于合作的常识问题
If you go and you collaborate to the extent
如果你合作到
that all you're doing is getting the information from somebody else,
所有的信息你都从别人那里获得的地步
you're not learning the material
你就什么都学不到
and you're not going to do well on the exams.
你就不能在考试中取得好成绩
In our experience, students who collaborate generally
依我们的经验，通常合作的学生
do better than students who work alone.
比单独一个人学习的表现会更好
But you owe it to yourself, if you're going to work in a study group,
如果要参加学习小组合作学习，你必须保证
to be prepared for your study group meeting.
你在小组讨论时是做了准备的
And specifically you should spend a half an hour to 45 minutes on each problem
讨论之前，每个问题你应该花半个小时到45分钟思考
before you go to group so you're up to speed
这样你就能进步的更快
and you've tried out your ideas.
而且你已经尝试过了你的想法
And you may have solutions to some, you may be stuck on some other ones,
你可能解决了一些问题，可能还有一些把你卡住了
but at least you applied yourself to it.
但是至少应该让自己有所准备
After 30 to 45 minutes, if you cannot get the problem,
30到45分钟后，如果你还是不能解决问题
just sitting there and banging your head against it makes no sense.
那你就不要再这个问题上浪费时间了
It's not a productive use of your time.
这是在做无用功
And I know most of you have issues with having time on your hands, right?
我想大家可以用这个时间，可以去做点别的什么
Like it's not there.
已经人在心不在了
So, don't go banging your head against problems that are too hard
这样的话，就不要在思考难题上浪费时间了
or where you don't understand what's going on or whatever.
就算完全弄不懂也没什么关系
That's when the study group can help out.
此时学习小组可以帮助解决问题
And, as I mentioned, we'll have homework labs which will
就像我说的那样，我们会有课外实验室
give you an opportunity to go and do that and coordinate with other students
这里可以和其他同学合作来找出答案
rather than necessarily having to form your own group.
不一定非得成立你自己的学习小组
And the TAs will be there.
也可以向助教请教
If your group is unable to solve the problem
如果你的小组不能解决你遇到的问题
then talk to other groups or ask your recitation instructor.
去其他小组尝试下，或者请教你的辅导老师
And, that's how you go about solving them.
这些都是可以解决问题的方法
Writing up the problem sets, however,
不过，写作业则是
is your individual responsibility and should be done alone.
你必须独立完成的过程，这是你的责任
You don't write up your problem solutions with other students,
你写答案的时候，不能与其它人讨论
you write them up on your own.
你必须独立作出解答
And you should on your problem sets,
而且在作业上…
because this is an academic place,
因为这里是做学术的地方
we understand that the source of academic information is very important,
我们知道学术信息来源是非常重要的
if you collaborated on solutions you should write a list of the collaborators.
如果是通过合作而得到的解决方案，你应该列出合作者名单
Say I worked with so and so on this solution.
说明合作情况
It does not affect your grade.
这不会影响你的评分
It's just a question of being scholarly.
这是学术研究的态度问题
It is a violation of this policy to submit a problem solution
如果你不能对授课工作人员完整口述你的问题解决方案
that you cannot orally explain to a member of the course staff.
这是明令禁止的
You say oh, well, my write-up is similar to that other person's.
你可能说，好吧，我所写的作业只是和其他人的类似
I didn't copy them.
我没有抄袭别人
We may ask you to orally explain your solution.
我们会要求你口述你的解决方案
If you are unable, according to this policy,
如果你不能完成，根据规定
the presumption is that you cheated.
你将被视为作弊
So, do not write up stuff that you don't understand.
因此，不要写下你不懂的东西
You should be able to write up the stuff that you understand.
按部就班去完成你所弄懂的
Understand why you're putting down what you're putting down.
总结解决问题的方法和方式
If it isn't obvious, no collaboration whatsoever is permitted on exams.
显然，考试中无论如何不会允许任何形式的合作
Exams is when we evaluate you.
考试是我们评估你的方式
And now we're not interested in evaluating other people,
我们不会对评估其他人感兴趣
we're interested in evaluating you.
我们唯一感兴趣的是评估你的学习情况
So, no collaboration on exams.
所以，考试中没有合作一说
We will have a take-home exam for the second quiz.
我们还会有课堂外的测试科目
You should look at the schedule.
你们可以看一下计划表
If there are problems with the schedule of that, we want to know early.
如果对于计划表有任何疑问，尽快去搞清楚
And we will give you more details about the collaboration
更多合作的细节
in the lecture on Monday, November 28th.
将在11月28号星期一的讲座中公布
Now, generally, the lectures here,
基本上我们都会在这里上课
they're mandatory and you have to know them,
你们必须清楚，这是没有商量的余地的
but I know that some people say gee, 9:30 is kind of early,
我知道一些人会抱怨，九点半太早了
especially on a Monday or whatever.
特别是在周一
It can be kind of early to get up.
早起是有益的
However, on Monday, November 28th,
11月28日周一
you fail the exam if you do not show up to lecture on time.
如果你不能出勤，你的考试也就没法及格
That one day you must show up.
至少那一天，你必须准时出勤
Any questions about that?
还有其他问题吗
That one day you must show up here,
那一天，准时出勤
even if you've been watching them on the Web.
即便你已经通过互联网看过一遍了
And generally, if you think you have transgressed,
如果有你发现自己违规了
the best is to come to us to talk about it.
最好的方式是来找我们交流
We can usually work something out.
我们通常会拿出解决办法来
It's when we find somebody has transgressed from a third-party
如果我们从第三方发现
or from obvious analyses that we do with homeworks,
或有明显迹象证明了任何人做作业时不规矩
that's when things get messy.
那就糟透了
So, if you think, for some reason or other, oh,
因此，如果因为某些原因
I may have done something wrong, please come and talk to us.
你认识到自己做了错误的事情，主动来找我们交流
We actually were students once, too, albeit many years ago.
我们曾经也是学生，虽然那是很多年前
Any questions? So, this class has great material.
还有其他问题吗? 这门课程的内容很棒
Fabulous material.
非常棒的内容
And it's really fun, but you do have to work hard.
而且十分有趣，但是大家必须努力
Let's talk content.
让我们进入正题
This is the topic of the first part of the course.
开始课程第一部分的主题
The first part of the course is focused on analysis.
这一部分将关注算法分析
The second part of the course is focused on design.
第二部分将主要介绍算法设计
Before you can do design,
在我们开始设计之前
you have to master a bunch of techniques for analyzing algorithms.
我们不得不掌握一些分析算法的实用技巧
And then you'll be in a position to design algorithms
然后你们将有能力设计算法
that you can analyze and that which are efficient.
并知道哪一种方式更有效
The analysis of algorithm is the theoretical study --
算法分析是理论研究
of computer program performance and resource usage.
是关于计算机程序性能和资源利用的研究
And a particular focus on performance.
特别关注性能
We're studying how to make things fast.
我们要学习如何让事情变得更快
In particular, computer programs.
尤其是计算机程序
We also will discover and talk about other resources
我们也将涉及并讨论其他的问题
such as communication, such as memory, whether RAM memory or disk memory.
例如通信，例如存储器，无论是内存还是磁盘存储
There are other resources that we may care about,
还有其他的内容我们同样需要关注
but predominantly we focus on performance.
但首先我们需要关注性能
Because this is a course about performance,
因为这是一门关注性能的学科
I like to put things in perspective a little bit by starting out and asking,
我喜欢用提问的方式，由浅入深的去分析问题
in programming, what is more important than performance?
在程序设计方面，什么是比性能更重要的呢？
If you're in an engineering situation and writing code, writing software,
如果你正处于一个软件工程环境，写代码，写软件
what's more important than performance?
什么比性能更重要呢？
Correctness. Good.
正确性，好
OK. What else?
还有其他的吗？
Simplicity can be. Very good. Yeah.
简洁，非常好
Maintainability often much more important than performance.
可维护性通常比性能更重要
Cost.
成本
And what type of cost are you thinking?
那种类型的成本或开销呢？
No, I mean cost of what?
不，我的意思是为此你付出了哪些代价？
We're talking software here, right?
我们正在讨论软件，是吗
What type of cost do you have in mind?
在你的脑海中存在哪些成本？
There are some costs that are involved when programming like programmer time.
我们经常碰到成本开销，例如程序员的时间成本
So, programmer time is another thing also that might be.
程序员的时间可能是另外一件需要考虑的事情
Stability.
稳定性
Robustness of the software.
软件的健壮性
Does it break all the time? What else?
它是否老崩溃；还有什么？
Come on. We've got a bunch of engineers here. A lot of things.
快，我们这里有很多工程师，应该有很多问题
How about features? Features can be more important.
特性呢？特性十分重要
Having a wider collection of features than your competitors.
比你的竞争对手拥有更多的特性集合
Functionality.
功能性
Modularity.
模块化
Is it designed in a way
它是否经由这样的设计方法
where you can make changes in a local part of the code
你只需要修改局部的代码
and you don't have to make changes across the code
避免修改全部代码
in order to affect a simple change in the functionality?
以便于影响功能中的简单变化
There is one big one which definitely, especially in the `90s,
还有一个很重要的因素，尤其是90年代
was like the big thing in computers.
对计算机而言意义重大
The big thing.
这是一件大事
Well, security actually. Good.
安全，很好
I don't even have that one down. Security is excellent.
我没有指出，但安全非常重要
That's actually been more in the 2000.
事实上到2000年以后
Security has been far more important often than performance.
安全已经变得比性能更加重要
Scalability has been important,
可扩展性也很重要
although scalability, in some sense, is performance related.
尽管在某种意义上，可扩展性与性能相关
But, yes, scalability is good.
但是，是的，可扩展性不容忽视
What was the big breakthrough
还有什么巨大的突破？
and why do people use Macintosh rather than Windows,
为什么人们更青睐苹果操作系统，而不是Windows？
those people who are of that religion?
这些人简直成了苹果的教徒？
User-friendliness.
用户友好
Wow. If you look at the number of cycles of computers
如果你一直关注计算机的发展历程
that went into user-friendliness in the `90s,
你就会见证90年代计算机是如何进入用户友好时代
it grew from almost nothing to
从几乎完全的空白状态直到
where it's now the vast part of the computation goes into user-friendly.
现在，大部分的计算设备都变得对用户友好了
So, all those things are more important than performance.
因此，所有的这些事情都比性能重要
This is a course on performance.
这是一门关于性能的课程
Then you can say OK, well,
你可能会有疑问
why do we bother and why study algorithms and performance
如果算法和性能都不重要
if it's at the bottom of the heap?
为什么我们还要学习？
Almost always people would rather have these other things than performance.
几乎总是有人在说其他的事情比性能更重要
You go off and you say to somebody,
你可能会纠结
would I rather have performance or more user-friendliness?
到底是要性能还是要更好的用户体验呢？
It's almost always more important than performance.
看似这些都比性能重要
Why do we care then? Yeah?
为什么我们还要关注性能？
That wasn't user-friendly.
那不是用户体验
Sometimes performance is correlated with user-friendliness, absolutely.
可以肯定的是，很多时候性能和用户体验是紧密联系在一起的
Nothing is more frustrating than sitting there waiting, right?
没有事情比坐着干等更令人沮丧的
So, that's a good reason.
因此，这是一个不错的理由
What are some other reasons why?
其他的原因是什么？
Sometimes they have real-time constraints
用户体验有时也有实时的限制
so they don't actually work unless they perform adequately.
如果性能达不到要求，用户体验难以保证
Yeah?
请讲
Hard to get, well, we don't usually quantify user-friendliness so I'm not sure,
难说，我们通常无法衡量用户体验，因此我不无法确定
but I understand what you're saying.
我理解你的意思
He says we don't get exponential performance improvements in user-friendliness.
他说在用户体验方面我们不能做到指数倍性能改进
We often don't get that in performance either, by the way.
当然，通常性能也不可能实现指数倍增长
Sometimes we do, but that's good.
但有些时候我们可以见证奇迹
There are several reasons that I think are important.
这里有几点重要的原因
One is that often performance
其一，通常性能的好与坏
measures the line between the feasible and the infeasible.
直接决定着可行还是不可行
We have heard some of these things.
我们听说过不少例子
For example, when there are real-time requirements,
例如，对于实时的需求
if it's not fast enough it's simply not functional.
程序不快，这只能表示它不可行
Or, if it uses too much memory it's simply not going to work for you.
或者，如果它占用过多的内存，也只能说是不可行
And, as a consequence,
所以
what you find is algorithms are on the cutting edge of entrepreneurship.
算法总是处于解决问题的最前沿
If you're talking about just re-implementing stuff
如果你讨论的只是重新实现
that people did ten years ago,
十年前人们就做过的东西
performance isn't that important at some level.
那某种意义上，性能就不再重要
But, if you're talking about doing stuff that nobody has done before,
但是如果你正在积极尝试其他人没有成功的事情
one of the reasons often that they haven't done it
之所以别人没有成功
is because it's too time-consuming.
因为太消耗时间
Things don't scale and so forth.
不具备可扩展的空间
So, that's one reason, is the feasible versus infeasible.
这是第一层原因，算法能够将不可行变成可行
Another thing is that
第二层原因
algorithms give you a language for talking about program behavior,
算法是一种描述程序行为的语言
and that turns out to be a language
它业已形成了一种语言
that has been pervasive through computer science,
一种已经广泛应用于计算机科学领域
is that the theoretical language is what gets adopted by all the practitioners
已经被所有的实践者所采用的理论语言
because it's a clean way of thinking about things.
它是一种让程序最为简洁的思考方式
A good way I think about performance,
我有一个很好的比喻来形容性能
and the reason it's on the bottom of the heap,
以及为何性能处于最底层
is sort of like performance is like money, it's like currency.
它所扮演的角色就如同经济中的货币一般
You say what good does a stack of hundred dollar bills do for you?
想想一沓一百美元的钞票有什么好的？
Wouldn't you rather have food or water or shelter or whatever?
你也许更需要有食物、水、房子等等
And you're willing to pay those hundred dollar bills for,
你需要用钞票才能…
if you have hundred dollar bills, for that commodity.
前提是你有的话，才能买下这些商品
Even though water is far more important to your living.
尽管水对于你的生命比钞票重要
Well, similarly, performance is what you use to pay for user-friendliness.
同样，性能是确保良好的用户体验的前提
It's what you pay for security.
也是安全的保障
And you hear people say, for example,
你可能听人说到
that I want greater functionality, so people will program in Java,
我希望有更多的功能，因此人们会用Java来写程序
even though it's much slower than C,
尽管它比C写的程序要慢很多
because they'll say it costs me maybe a factor of three or something
他们会说用Java编程性能会损失三倍左右
in performance to program in Java. But Java is worth it
但是值得为Java付出这些代价
because it's got all these object-oriented features and so forth,
因为它提供面向对象的特性
exception mechanisms and so on.
以及异常机制等等
And so people are willing to pay a factor of three in performance.
所以人们能够接受三倍的性能损失
So, that's why you want performance
这就是为什么你需要性能
because you can use it to pay for these other things that you want.
因为你需要性能作为支付其他东西的"货币"
And that's why, in some sense, it's on the bottom of the heap,
在某种意义上，这就是为什么性能是处于最底层的原因
because it's the universal thing that you quantify.
因为它是衡量的一般性标准
Do you want to spend a factor of two on this
你愿意消耗两倍的性能在这上面
or spend a factor of three on security, et cetera?
还是消耗三倍的性能在安全上呢，等等
And, in addition, the lessons generalize to other resource measures
另外，其他资源方面同样适用
like communication, like memory and so forth.
例如通信、内存等等
And the last reason we study algorithm performance is it's tons of fun.
我们学习算法性能最后一个原因是，这里充满了乐趣
Speed is always fun, right?
速度永远让人渴望，是吗？
Why do people drive fast cars, race horses, whatever?
为什么人们喜欢驾驶跑车、赛马这些快速的东西？
Rockets, et cetera, why do we do that? Because speed is fun.
例如火箭，为什么？因为我们向往速度
Ski. Who likes to ski? I love to ski.
滑雪，为什么你热爱滑雪
I like going fast on those skis. It's fun.
我喜欢在雪地中快速飞驰，这很有趣
Hockey, fast sports, right? We all like the fast sports.
冰球，刺激的运动，我们都喜欢快速刺激的运动
Not all of us, I mean. Some people say he's not talking to me.
也不是所有人啦，有些人会说他们与我道不同不相为谋
OK, let's move on.
好吧，让我们继续
That's sort of a little bit of a notion as to why we study this,
这是为什么学习算法的一些基本概念
is that it does, in some sense,
在某种意义上
form a common basis for all these other things we care about.
这些是开展后续课程的基本前提
And so we want to understand
我们希望知道
how can we generate money for ourselves in computation?
如何才能让计算转化为金钱
We're going to start out with a very simple problem.
让我们从一个非常简单的问题开始
It's one of the oldest problems that has been studied in algorithms,
这是一个在算法学习中最古老的问题
is the problem of sorting.
就是排序问题
We're going to actually study this for several lectures
我们将用几个课时来介绍它
because sorting contains many algorithmic techniques.
排序包含了很多基本的算法
The sorting problem is the following.
举一个排序的例子
We have a sequence a_1, a_2 up to a_n of numbers as input.
我们输入一组序列a₁, a₂直到an
And our output is a permutation of those numbers.
按照需求重新排列后作为输出
A permutation is a rearrangement of the numbers.
排列是指对一组数字的重新排序
Every number appears exactly once in the rearrangement such that,
排序后每个数字出现且仅出现一次，使得…
I sometimes use a dollar sign to mean "such that,"
我有时会用$符号来表示“使得”
such that a_1 is less than or equal to a_2 prime.
使得a₁'≤a₂'≤…
Such that they are monotonically increasing in size.
使得它们的大小单调递增
Take a bunch of numbers, put them in order.
输入一组数字，将它们按一定顺序排列
Here's an algorithm to do it. It's called insertion sort.
这里有一种算法来完成这项工作，称为插入排序
And we will write this algorithm in what we call pseudocode.
我们将用伪代码来描述此算法
It's sort of a programming language, except it's got English in there often.
伪代码与编程语言很类似，只是经常会包含一些英语在里面
And it's just a shorthand for writing for being precise.
伪代码能够让我们更容易理解算法所要表达的意思
So this sorts A from 1 to n.
从第一项到第n项排序
And here is the code for it.
下面是它的代码
This is what we call pseudocode.
这就是我们所说的伪代码
And if you don't understand the pseudocode
如果你不理解伪代码
then you should ask questions about any of the notations.
你可以就不理解的符号进行提问
You will start to get used to it as we go on.
今后你们将习惯使用伪代码
One thing is that in the pseudocode we use indentation,
值得一提的是我们在伪代码中使用缩进
where in most languages they have some kind of begin-end delimiters
相当于在大多数语言中标注开始和结束的分隔符
like curly braces or something in Java or C, for example.
好比Java和C中使用的大括号
We just use indentation.
伪代码中只使用缩进
The whole idea of the pseudocode is to try to get the algorithms as short as possible
伪代码的目的是让算法的表达尽量简洁
while still understanding what the individual steps are.
同时表达每一步的含义
In practice, there actually have been languages
实际上，还真有过一些编程语言
that use indentation as a means of showing the nesting of things.
使用缩进来表示嵌套的意义
It's generally a bad idea, because if things go over one page to another,
这不是一个好主义，比如当代码换页时
for example, you cannot tell what level of nesting it is.
你很难知道自己在哪一个嵌套的层级
Whereas, with explicit braces it's much easier to tell.
而使用大括号会清晰明了得多
So, there are reasons
所以，这就是为什么说
why this is a bad notation if you were doing software engineering.
在软件工程中用缩进表示嵌套并非好事的原因
But it's a good one for us
但对于研究算法
because it just keeps things short and makes fewer things to write down.
它是不错的选择，因为这让我们的代码简短、容易书写
So, this is insertion sort.
这就是插入排序
Let's try to figure out a little bit what this does.
让我们来一步一步的看看它是如何工作的
It basically takes an array A and at any point the thing to understand is,
首先构造数组A，需要理解的是
we're setting basically, we're running the outer loop from j is 2 to n,
设置外部循环条件，j为从2到n递增
and the inner loop that starts at j minus 1
而内部循环条件开始于j-1
and then goes down until it's zero.
并递减至0
Basically, if we look at any point in the algorithm,
基本上算法中的任意一步是这样的
we essentially are looking at some element here j.
我们找到j
A of j, the jth element.
数组A的第j个位置
And what we do essentially is we pull a value out here that we call the key.
我们把这个位置的值提取出来，在这里称之为键值(key)
And at this point the important thing to understand,
在这里有一点很重要
and we'll talk more about this in recitation on Friday,
我们也会在周五的助教课中再次谈到
is that there is an invariant
即存在一个常量
that is being maintained by this loop each time through.
每次循环后这个常量保持不变
And the invariant is that this part of the array is sorted.
常量就是数组已经被排序过的这部分
And the goal each time through the loop is to increase,
每次循环的目的是完成增量
is to add one to the length of the things that are sorted.
就是使已排序部分的长度增加1
And the way we do that is we pull out the key
实现方法是提取当前循环中位置为j的数字键
and we just copy values up like this.
然后我们就一直这样复制值
And keep copying up until we find the place where this key goes,
一步步把前面的值抄到下一位上，直到找到此键合适的位置
and then we insert it in that place.
然后我们插入键值
And that's why it's called insertion sort.
这就是称之为插入排序的原因
We just sort of move the things,
我们在数组中移动元素的位置
copy the things up until we find where it goes,
持续复制这些元素直到我们找到它们的适当位置
and then we put it into place.
并将它们放置到这些位置中去
And now we have it from A from one to j is sorted,
至此，从数组A中的数字已经从1到j的位置排列好
and now we can work on j plus one.
现在我们可以来执行j+1
Let's give an example of that.
这里有一个具体的实例
Imagine we are doing 8, 2, 4, 9, 3, 6.
给定数组8，2，4，9，3，6
We start out with j equals 2.
我们首先设定j从数字2的位置开始
And we figure out that we want to insert it there.
然后找到我们希望插入的位置
Now we have 2, 8, 4, 9, 3, 6.
得到2，8，4，9，3，6
Then we look at the four and say oh, well, that goes over here.
然后我们再找到4，按照排序规则移动
We get 2, 4, 8, 9, 3, 6 after the second iteration of the outer loop.
执行第二次循环，我们得到2，3，8，9，3，6
Then we look at 9 and discover immediately it just goes right there.
找到数字9，我们发现它已经处于正确位置
Very little work to do on that step.
直接跳过
So, we have exactly the same output after that iteration.
这个循环没有任何变化
Then we look at the 3 and that's going to be inserted over there.
然后考虑数字3，执行循环插到这里
2, 3, 4, 8, 9, 6.
现在是2, 3, 4, 8, 9, 6
And finally we look at the 6 and that goes in there.
最终考虑数字6，并执行循环移到这里
2, 3, 4, 6, 8, 9.
得到2, 3, 4, 6, 8, 9.
And at that point we are done.
问题解决了
Question?
大家有没有问题？
The array initially starts at one, yes.
我们的数组下标从1开始，对
A[1..n], OK?
A[1到n]
So, this is the insertion sort algorithm.
好了，这就是插入排序算法
And it's the first algorithm that we're going to analyze.
并且它是我们要着手分析的第一个算法
And we're going to pull out some tools that we have from our math background
我们会找一些数学工具
help to analyze it.
来分析这个算法
First of all, let's take a look at the issue of running time.
首先，让我们来关注一下运行时间的问题
The running time depends, of this algorithm depends on a lot of things.
算法的运行时间取决于诸多因素
One thing it depends on is the input itself.
其中一个因素是输入本身
For example, if the input is already sorted --
举例而言，如果输入已经有序
then insertion sort has very little work to do.
那末插入排序要做的工作就十分之少了
Because every time through it's going to be like this case.
因为每次遍历，它做的事都如此这般
It doesn't have to shuffle too many guys over
它没有必要整理太多东西
because they're already in place.
因为它们已经各就各位了
Whereas, in some sense, what's the worst case for insertion sort?
那么从这种意义上讲，什么是插入排序的最坏情况呢？
If it is reverse sorted then it's going to have to do a lot of work
最坏的是逆序情形，此时算法必须做大量的工作
because it's going to have to shuffle everything over on each step of the outer loop.
因为这么一来，它就不得不把所有的元素都重新整理一遍
In addition to the actual input it depends, of course, on the input size.
除此之外，当然，算法的运行时间还取决于输入规模
Here, for example, we did six elements.
比如在这里，我们一共要处理六个元素
It's going to take longer if we, for example,
但如果要处理六十亿个元素的话
do six times ten to the ninth elements.
它就需要花上长很多的时间
If we were sorting a lot more stuff, it's going to take us a lot longer.
这就是说要处理的输入规模越大，所花费的运行时间也越长
Typically, the way we handle that is
通常，我们处理输入规模的方式是
we are going to parameterize things in the input size.
我们将依输入的规模将其参数化
We are going to talk about time as a function of the size of things that we are sorting
以后，我们会把运行时间看作待排列数据规模的函数
so we can look at what is the behavior of that.
这么一来，我们在审视算法的行为时就有依据了
And the last thing I want to say about running time is generally
关于运行时间，我最后想谈一下的是
we want upper bonds on the running time.
一般来说，我们都想知道运行时间的上界
We want to know that the time is no more than a certain amount.
也就是说我们想知道运行时间是不会超过某个特定量的
And the reason is because that represents a guarantee to the user.
原因在于，这代表了对用户的一种承诺
If I say it's not going to run, for example,
如果我说，这个程序不会运行超过某个时间，例如
if I tell you here's a program and it won't run more than three seconds,
我告诉你，这个程序，它的运行时间不会超过三秒钟
that gives you real information about how you could use it,
这就是给了你一个有关你将如何使用该程序的真实信息
Whereas, if I said here's a program and it goes at least three seconds,
反之，如果我告诉你这个程序至少会运行三秒钟
you don't know if it's going to go for three years.
你就拿不准它会不会运行上三年时间了
It doesn't give you that much guarantee if you are a user of it.
那末这样的信息就不能当作给用户提供的承诺了
Generally we want upper bonds
再说一遍，我们一般想获得运行时间的上界
because it represents a guarantee to the user.
因为它代表了对用户的承诺
There are different kinds of analyses that people do.
人们会对算法做各种各样的分析
The one we're mostly going to focus on is
我们将要最关注的一种分析
what's called worst-case analysis.
就是所谓的最坏情况分析
And this is what we do usually where
我们通常最关注这个
we define T of n to be the maximum time on any input of size n.
T(n)定义为输入规模为n时的最长运行时间
So, it's the maximum input,
它是输入规模为n时
the maximum it could possibly cost us on an input of size n.
程序运行的最长可能消耗时间
What that does is, if you look at the fact
这个结果的意义是
that sometimes the inputs are better and sometimes they're worse,
如果你检视一下这个事实，输入有好有坏
we're looking at the worst case of those
我们所关注的，正是所有输入中的最坏情况
because that's the way we're going to be able to make a guarantee.
因为，只有这样我们才可以作出承诺
It always does something rather than just sometimes does something.
这种算法总能做到这样，而不是有时能
So, we're looking at the maximum.
是故，我们现在关注的是最大值
Notice that if I didn't have maximum
请注意，若是我们得不到最大值
then T(n) in some sense is a relation, not a function,
那么T(n)在某种意义上只能算一种相关性，而不能算函数
because the time on an input of size n depends on which input of size n.
因为它还牵扯到该输入规模n之下到底是怎么样的一个输入
I could have many different times,
这样我就可以得到好多不同的时间结果
but by putting the maximum at it,
但一旦我说我要的是最大值
it turns that relation into a function
结果就成为了一种函数关系
because there's only one maximum time that it will take.
因为只有一个最长时间作为结果
Sometimes we will talk about average case.
有时，我们也会讨论平均情况
Sometimes we will do this.
有时我们会这样做
Here T of n is then the expected time over all inputs of size n.
这里T(n)就成了输入规模n之下所有可能输入的期望时间
It's the expected time.
记住，是时间的期望值哟
Now, if I talk about expected time, what else do I need to say here?
讲到期望值，还需要讲到什么？
What does that mean, expected time? I'm sorry.
什么是期望时间？哪位说知道
Raise your hand.
请举手
Expected inputs. What does that mean, expected inputs?
期望输入。这又是什么意思，期望输入？
I need more math.
我想听到更有数学味儿的回答
What do I need by expected time here, math?
我这里说期望时间是什么意思，往数学方面想？
You have to take the time of every input and then average them, OK.
要把所有输入的运行时间加起来然后求平均值
That's kind of what we mean by expected time.
这接近我要讲的期望时间了
Good.
有点儿靠谱了
Not quite.
但还不是那么好
I mean, what you say is completely correct, except is not quite enough.
我是说，你说的完全正确，但就是还不太到位
Yeah?
什么？
It's the time of every input times the probability that it will be that input.
这应该是每种输入的运行时间，乘以那种输入出现的概率
It's a way of taking a weighted average, exactly right.
这是一种加权平均，完全正确
How do I know what the probability of every input is?
那我又如何知道每种输入出现的概率是多少？
How do I know what the probability a particular input occurs is in a given situation?
我如何知道某种特定输入在给定情形下出现的概率是多少？
I don't.
我不可能知道
I have to make an assumption.
我得作出假设
What's that assumption called?
那我要做什么样的假设？
What kind of assumption do I have to meet?
在这个假设中我需要满足些什么条件呢？
I need an assumption --
我需要一个假设
of the statistical distribution of inputs.
一个有关输入的统计分布的假设
Otherwise, expected time doesn't mean anything
否则的话，期望时间就无从谈起
because I don't know what the probability of something is.
因为我不清楚某种东西的可能性是怎么样的
In order to do probability, you need some assumptions
为了计算概率，你就要做一些假设
and you've got to state those assumptions clearly.
并且，你需要将这些假设说明得一清二楚
One of the most common assumptions is
最常见的假设之一就是
that all inputs are equally likely.
所有输入都是以等可能的方式出现的
That's called the uniform distribution.
即所谓均匀分布
Every input of size n is equally likely, that kind of thing.
所有规模为n的输入情况都是等可能地出现
But there are other ways that you could make that assumption,
但也有其他方法来做这样的假设
and they may not all be true.
并且它们可能并不都是对的
This is much more complicated, as you can see.
这个就复杂多了，如你们所见
Fortunately, all of you have a strong probability background.
好在，你们都有很不错的概率背景
And so we will not have any trouble addressing
所以，我们不会
these probabilistic issues of dealing with expectations and such.
在有关期望等诸如此类的概率问题上遇到拦路虎
If you don't, time to go and say gee, maybe I should take that Probability class
如果情况不是这样，也许你会后悔：真该学学概率论的
that is a prerequisite for this class.
它是这门课的先修课程
The last one I am going to mention is best-case analysis.
我最后想讲一讲的是最好情况分析
And this I claim is bogus.
对于这个，我称之为假象
Bogus.
假象
No good.
没啥用
Why is best-case analysis bogus? Yeah?
为什么最好情况分析是假象？嗯？
The best-case probably doesn't ever happen.
最好的情况可能永远不会出现
Actually, it's interesting because for the sorting problem,
事实上，这很有趣，因为对于排序问题
the most common things that get sorted are things
最常见的是我们打算加以排序的
that are already sorted interestingly,
都已以某种有意思的方式作了一定的排序
or at least almost sorted.
或差不多排好了序
For example, one of the most common things
例如，欲加以排序的最常见的
that are sorted is check numbers by banks.
是银行的支票号码
They tend to come in, in the same order that they are written.
它们被送入的顺序，往往与被签写的顺序相同
They're sorting things that are almost always sorted.
它们就是“已经差不多被排好序的被排序物”
I mean, it's good. But... OK, you want to...
我的意思是说，这不赖…你说…
When upper bond, not lower bound?
什么时候我们要上界，不要下界？
Yeah, you want to make a guarantee.
对，在你想作出承诺的时候
And so why is this not a guarantee?
那么，为什么下界就不是一个保证呢？
You're onto something there,
你的确说出了一些东西
but we need a little more precision here.
但这里我们需要更多一点的精确性
How can I cheat? Yeah?
为什么说这是欺骗？嗯？
Yeah, you can cheat.
对，你可以骗到人
You cheat.
你这样骗
You take any slow algorithm that you want
你采用你想要的任何效率低下的算法
and just check for some particular input,
然后你只对某些特定输入检验它
and if it's that input, then you say immediately yeah,
如果输入正好就是那个最好的，你马上说
OK, here is the answer.
“好了，你要的答案有了”
And then it's got a good best-case.
然后，你就得到了“好得很”的最好情况
But I didn't tell you anything about
可是你并没有说明绝大多数情况下
the vast majority of what is going on.
将会发生什么的任何信息
So, you can cheat with a slow algorithm
所以，你可以采用一个慢速算法
that works fast on some input.
但它对于某些输入很快
It doesn't really do much for you
这种信息没什么大用
Let's see.
我们来看看
What is insertion sorts worst-case time?
插入排序的最坏情况时间是多少？
Now we get into some sort of funny issues.
现在我们遇到了一些有趣的事儿
First of all, it sort of depends on the computer you're running on.
首先，它取决于运行它的计算机
Whose computer, right?
谁的计算机，对吗？
Is it a big supercomputer or is it your wristwatch?
它是个大型超级计算机，还是仅仅是你的腕表芯片？
They have different computational abilities.
它们的计算能力大相径庭
And when we compare algorithms, we compare them typically for relative speed.
而当我们比较算法时，我们通常比较的是其相对速度
This is if you compared two algorithms on the same machine.
也就是两个算法在同一台机器上的表现
You could argue, well, it doesn't really matter what the machine is
你可能会说，那好，什么机器都无所谓
because I will just look at their relative speed.
因为我只想知道它们的相对速度
But, of course, I may also be interested in absolute speed.
但是，理所当然，我可能也对其绝对速度感兴趣
Is one algorithm actually better no matter what machine it's run on?
真有某种算法能无论在什么机器上运行都表现得更好吗？
And so this kind of gets sort of confusing as to how I can talk
诸如此类的言论
about the worst-case time of an algorithm of a piece of software
在我谈论某个软件算法而不涉及硬件时
when I am not talking about the hardware
对最坏情况时间而言会造成一些迷惑
because, clearly, if I had run on a faster machine,
因为，显然，如果我在一台更快的计算机上运行
my algorithms are going to go faster.
我的算法会跑得更快
So, this is where you get the big idea of algorithms.
所以，这里我们就要谈到算法的大局观
Which is why algorithm is such a huge field,
这也是为什么算法涉猎如此广泛
why it spawns companies
以及为什么算法可以催生
like Google, like Akamai, like Amazon.
像Google、Akamai和Amzon这样的巨头
Why algorithmic analysis, throughout the history of computing,
为什么算法分析，在整个计算史上
has been such a huge success, is our ability to master
取得过如此辉煌的成功，为何我们可以掌握
and to be able to take what is apparently a really messy, complicated situation
并对付那些看起来一团迷局、复杂无比的局面
and reduce it to being able to do some mathematics.
把它们简化到可以采用一些数学手段处理的程度
And that idea is called asymptotic analysis.
那样的一种观点，就是所谓的渐近分析
And the basic idea of asymptotic analysis
而渐近分析的基本思路
is to ignore machine-dependent constants --
则是忽略掉那些依赖于机器的常量
and, instead of the actual running time,
以及，不是去检查实际的运行时间
look at the growth of the running time.
而是关注运行时间的增长
So, we don't look at the actual running time.
所以，我们不关注实际的运行时间
We look at the growth.
我们只关注它如何增长
Let's see what we mean by that.
我们看一下这是什么意思
This is a huge idea.
这种思路很伟大
It's not a hard idea,
但并不难理解
otherwise I wouldn't be able to teach it in the first lecture,
不然的话我也不可能在第一讲就拿出来教给你们
but it's a huge idea.
但这个思路的确非常伟大
We are going to spend a couple of lectures understanding the implications of that
我们要花费数讲的时间来理解它的内涵
and will basically be doing it throughout the term.
而且本质上说，我们整个学期就是在做这么一件事
And if you go on to be practicing engineers, you will be doing it all the time.
而且你成为一线工程师的话，成天就干这个
In order to do that, we adopt some notations that are going to help us.
为了做这件事，就要采用一些有助于我们理解的符号
In particular, we will adopt asymptotic notation.
尤其是，我们要采用渐近符号
Most of you have seen some kind of asymptotic notation.
你们中的大多数已经了解了一些渐近符号
Maybe a few of you haven't, but mostly you should have seen a little bit.
也许有些同学还没见过，但大多数应该多少见过几个
The one we're going to be using in this class predominantly is theta notation.
其中一个我们要在这门课里使用的主要符号叫θ符号
And theta notation is pretty easy notation to master because all you do is,
θ符号掌握起来很简单，你要做的就是
from a formula, just drop low order terms and ignore leading constants.
写个公式，弃去它的低阶项，并忽略前面的常数因子
For example, if I have a formula like 3n^3 + 90n^2 - 5n + 6046,
例如，如果公式为3n³+90n²-5n+6046
I say, well, what low-order terms do I drop? Well, n^3 is a bigger term than n^2.
我就看什么是要弃去的低阶项？n³比n²阶数高
I am going to drop all these terms and ignore the leading constant,
所以我把这些都弃去，把前面的常数因子也忽略掉
so I say that's Theta(n^3).
所以我就说，这个公式是θ(n³)的
That's pretty easy.
简单吧？
So, that's theta notation.
这就是θ符号
Now, this is an engineering way of manipulating theta notation.
现在，操纵θ符号都已经有了工程方法了
There is actually a mathematical definition for this,
其实它有个数学定义
which we are going to talk about next time,
我们下次再说这个
which is a definition in terms of sets of functions.
具体而言，它有一种函数定义
And, you are going to be responsible,
而且，你们得负起责任
this is both a math and a computer science engineering class.
因为这既是一门数学课又是一门计算机科学工程课
Throughout the course you are going to be responsible
在整个课程中，你们担负着双重责任
both for mathematical rigor as if it were a math course
你们既要像对待数学课那样有数学的严谨
and engineering commonsense because it's an engineering course.
又得像工程课那样富于直觉
We are going to be doing both.
我们两者都要满足
This is the engineering way of understanding what you do,
这里讲的是让你理解在做什么的工程途径
so you're responsible for being able to do these manipulations.
所以你就要负责学会如此这般进行运算
You're also going to be responsible
你们同样也要负责
for understanding the mathematical definition of theta notion
理解θ符号的数学定义
and of its related O notation and omega notation.
以及和它相关的大O符号和Ω符号
If I take a look as n approaches infinity,
如果我关注当n趋向于无穷大的情况
a Theta(n^2) algorithm always beats,
就知道一个θ(n²)的算法
eventually, a Theta(n^3) algorithm.
迟早会战胜一个θ(n³)的算法
As n gets bigger, it doesn't matter what these other terms were
假如我用公式来描述这个精确的行为，当n变大时
if I were describing the absolute precise behavior in terms of a formula.
其它项是什么都不能动摇这个结果
If I had a Theta(n^2) algorithm,
假如我有一个θ(n²)的算法
it would always be faster for sufficiently large n than a Theta(n^3) algorithm.
总有某个充分大的n使得它比θ(n³)的算法快
It wouldn't matter what those low-order terms were.
无论那些低阶项是什么都影响不了这个结果
It wouldn't matter what the leading constant was.
无论常数项是多少也不会动摇这个结果
This one will always be faster.
这个算法永远会更快
Even if you ran the Theta(n^2) algorithm on a slow computer
即使你在一台慢速计算机上运行这个θ(n²)算法
and the Theta(n^3) algorithm on a fast computer.
而在一台高速计算机上运行这个θ(n³)算法
The great thing about asymptotic notation is
渐近符号的伟大之处在于
it satisfies our issue of being able to compare both relative and absolute speed,
它能一举满足我们对相对和绝对速度的双重比较要求
because we are able to do this no matter what the computer platform.
因为我们在无论什么计算平台上都能实现这一点
On different platforms we may get different constants here,
在不同的平台上我们也许只是差个常数因子
machine-dependent constants for the actual running time,
就是有关运行时间的机器相关的常数因子
but if I look at the growth as the size of the input gets larger,
但是如果我关注随着输入规模变大的时间增长
the asymptotics generally won't change.
渐近结果一般而言不会改变
For example, I will just draw that as a picture.
举个例子，我画个图给大家看
If I have n on this axis and T(n) on this axis.
这条轴是n，那条是T(n)
This may be, for example,
这个，也许是
a Theta(n^3) algorithm and this may be a Theta(n^2) algorithm.
一个θ(n³)的算法而那是一个θ(n²)的算法
There is always going to be some point n_o
总会有某个点n₀
where for everything larger the Theta(n^2) algorithm
比它大的任何数，θ(n²)的算法
is going to be cheaper than the Theta(n^3) algorithm
都比θ(n³)有更小的开销
not matter how much advantage you give it at the beginning
不管你一开始给后者多大的优势
in terms of the speed of the computer you are running on.
在计算机的运行速度等方面给再大优势都没用
Now, from an engineering point of view,
现在，以工程视角来看
there are some issues we have to deal with
有一些问题我们还是要处理
because sometimes it could be that that n_o is so large
因为有的时候，这样的n₀是过大了
that the computers aren't big enough to run the problem.
大到计算机无法运行该算法
That's why we, nevertheless, are interested in some of the slower algorithms,
这就是为什么我们有时会对一些相对低速的算法有兴趣
because some of the slower algorithms,
因为有些这样的低速算法
even though they may not asymptotically be slower,
尽管用渐近的观点来看，它们有可能较慢
They may still be faster on reasonable sizes of things.
它们仍然可以在合理规模的输入下运行得更快
And so we have to both balance our mathematical understanding
因此，我们就必须在我们的数学理解
with our engineering common sense in order to do good programming.
和工程直觉之间作好权衡才能写出好用的程序
So, just having done analysis of algorithms
所以，仅仅会做算法分析
doesn't automatically make you a good programmer.
并不能使你自动地成为一个编程高手
You also need to learn how to program and use these tools in practice
你还需要学习怎样编程以及在实践中运用这些工具
to understand when they are relevant and when they are not relevant.
这样才能了解什么时候它们相关，什么时候又不相关
There is a saying.
有一种说法
If you want to be a good programmer,
如果你想成为一个编程高手
you just program ever day for two years, you will be an excellent programmer.
只要两年中每天坚持编程，你就能成为编程高手
If you want to be a world-class programmer,
如果你想成为一名世界级的大牛
you can program every day for ten years,
你既可以十年如一日每天坚持编程
or you can program every day for two years and take an algorithms class.
也可以两年中每天编程，然后上一门算法课
Let's get back to what we were doing, which is analyzing insertion sort.
言归正传，继续做插入排序的分析
We are going to look at the worse-case.
我们看看最坏情况
Which, as we mentioned before, is when the input is reverse sorted.
这就我们刚才说的，逆向排好序的情形
The biggest element comes first and the smallest last
最大元素占首，最小元素断后
because now every time you do the insertion you've got to shuffle everything over.
此时每次做插入操作你总要把所有项翻动一遍
You can write down the running time by looking at the nesting of loops.
你可以看看循环嵌套的情况，写下运行时间
What we do is we sum up.
我们要做的就是求和
What we assume is that every operation,
我们假设，每一种操作
every elemental operation is going to take some constant amount of time.
每一种原子操作都耗费某常数时间
But we don't have to worry about what that constant is
这个常数是多少，无关紧要
because we're going to be doing asymptotic analysis.
因为我们做的是渐近分析
As I say, the beautify of the method is
如我所说，这种方法的妙处在于
that it causes all these things that are real distinctions to sort of vanish.
它会使得诸多彼此各异的麻烦一举消失
We sort of look at them from 30,000 ft
我们就像是从三万英尺的高度看整件事
rather than from 3 mm or something.
而不是从三毫米的距离
Each of these operations is going to sort of be a basic operation.
这里的每项操作都差不多是某种基本操作
One way to think about this, in terms of counting operations,
我们进行操作数目计数的一种办法
is counting memory references.
叫做内存引用计数
How many times do you actually access some variable?
你实际上访问了某个变量多少次？
That's another way of sort of thinking about this model.
这就是思考这个问题的另一种思路
When we do that, well, we're going to go through this loop,
当我们来做这件事时，好吧，我们遍历该循环
j is going from 2 to n,
j是从2循环到n
and then we're going to add up the work that we do within the loop.
我们把循环里的所有工作全部汇总
We can sort of write that in math as summation of j equals 2 to n.
我们可以写成数学里的求和号，j是从2到n
And then what is the work that is going on in this loop?
然后，循环体中做了哪些工作呢？
Well, the work that is going on in this loop varies,
好，循环中进行的工作量有各种可能
but in the worst case
但考虑最坏情况
how many operations are going on here for each value of j?
对于j的每一个取值，会做多少次操作呢？
For a given value of j, how much work goes on in this loop?
对于给定的j值，循环将做多少次操作？
Can somebody tell me asymptotically?
有没有人能用渐近的语言告诉我？
Asymptotically, it's j times some constant, so it's theta j.
渐近上，这等于j乘上某个常数，所以应该是θ(j)
So, there is theta j work going on here
因此，那里会发生θ(j)次操作
because this loop starts out with i being j minus 1,
因为内循环里的i以j-1作为初值
and then it's doing just a constant amount of stuff for each step of the value of i,
然后它在i每次取新值时只做固定量的工作
and i is running from j minus one down to zero.
而i则从是从j-1步降至0
So, we can say that is theta j work that is going on.
所以我们说那里做了θ(j)数量的工作
Do people follow that?
你们跟得上我讲的吗？
And now we have a formula we can evaluate.
现在我们得到了一个可用以计算的公式了
What is the evaluation?
怎么计算呢？
If I want to simplify this formula, what is that equal to?
如果我想化简该公式，它等于什么呢？
Sorry. In the back there.
不好意思，后面那位
Yeah. OK.
好，对了
That's just Theta(n^2), good.
这就是个θ(n²)的算法，对
Because when you're saying is the sum of consecutive numbers, you mean what?
因为这相当于对连续整数求和，什么意思呢？
What's the mathematic term we have for that so we can communicate?
有个什么数学术语可以描述它呢？
You've got to know these things so you can communicate.
你得知道这些术语，才能顺利沟通
It's called what type of sequence?
这就是所谓的哪种数列来着？
It's actually a series, but that's OK.
实际上它是一种级数，不过没关系
What type of series is this called?
这叫什么级数？
Arithmetic series, good.
算术级数，很好
Wow, we've got some sharp people who can communicate.
哇，我们中间颇有一些高手，沟通就好办了
This is an arithmetic series.
这是个算术级数
You're basically summing 1 + 2 + 3 + 4, some constants in there,
你基本上是像1+2+3+4这样一些常数求和
but basically it's 1 + 2 + 3 + 4 + 5 + 6 up to n.
但说到底它是1+2+3+4+5+6一直加到n
That's Theta(n^2).
这当然是θ(n²)的
If you don't know this math,
你要是不懂这部分的数学
there is a chapter in the book, or you could have taken the prerequisite.
书中专门有一章你可以看看，或者还是老话，去修预备课程
Arithmetic series.
算术级数
People have this vague recollection. Oh, yeah.
你们总算还有点儿印象，对
Good.
好
Now, you have to learn these manipulations.
现在，你必须学会这些运算
We will talk about a bit next time,
我们下次还会提一些这个内容
but you have to learn your theta manipulations for what works with theta.
但你得学会θ运算，并了解θ符号是做什么的
And you have to be very careful because theta is a weak notation.
并且你要特别小心，因为θ是一种弱符号
A strong notation is something like Leibniz notation from calculus
强符号是像微积分中莱布尼茨符号这样的东西
where the chain rule is just canceling two things.
用它，链式法则可以直接约分消项
It's just fabulous that you can cancel in the chain rule.
能在链式法则内消项是很神奇的事
And Leibniz notation just expresses that so directly you can manipulate.
莱布尼茨符号的表达那么直接，以至于你可以直接运算
Theta notation is not like that.
θ符号不是这样的
If you think it is like that you are in trouble.
如果你认为它是这样的，你就有麻烦了
You really have to think of what is going on under the theta notation.
你得想明白θ符号背后究竟做了什么工作
And it is more of a descriptive notation than it is a manipulative notation.
与其说它是个运算符号，不如说它是个描述符号
There are manipulations you can do with it,
你的确可以用它来进行一些运算
but unless you understand what is really going on
但除非你明白是怎么回事
under the theta notation you will find yourself in trouble.
否则在θ符号下你会发现自己陷入麻烦
And next time we will talk a little bit more about theta notation.
下次我们会讲更多有关θ符号的内容
Is insertion sort fast?
插入排序快不快？
Well, it turns out for small n it is moderately fast.
嗯，对于很小的n，它挺快的
But it is not at all for large n.
但是对于巨大的n就完全不是那么回事了
So, I am going to give you an algorithm that is faster.
所以我要给你一个更快的算法
It's called merge sort.
叫做归并排序
I wonder if I should leave insertion sort up.
插入排序还留着吗
Why not.
干嘛不呢
I am going to write on this later,
这里的我呆会儿写
so if you are taking notes, leave some space on the left.
如果你要做笔记，在左边留点空
Here is merge sort of an array A from 1 up to n.
这是对于数组A[1..n]的归并排序
And it is basically three steps.
它有三个基本步骤
If n equals 1 we are done.
如果n是1，那我们做完了
Sorting one element, it is already sorted.
对一个元素排序，那它已经是排好序的
All right.
好
Recursive algorithm.
递归算法
Otherwise,
否则
what we do is we recursively sort A from 1 up to the ceiling of n over 2.
我们做的就是递归地对A[1到n/2向上取整]这部分
And the array A of the ceiling of n over 2 plus one up to n.
以及A[n/2+1向上取整..n]这部分排序
So, we sort two halves of the input.
所以，我们的输入是分成两半的
And then, three, we take those two lists that we have done and we merge them.
然后，第三步，我们把排好序的两个表归并
And, to do that,
而且，为了实现这一点
we use a merge subroutine which I will show you.
我们用了一个归并子程序，一会儿给你看
The key subroutine here is merge, and it works like this.
关键的子程序在于归并，它是这样做的
I have two lists. Let's say one of them is 20.
两张表，假定其中一张有20…
I am doing this in reverse order. I have sorted this like this.
我按相反顺序做，先对它这样排序
And then I sort another one.
然后我同样排序另一张表
I don't know why I do it this order, but anyway.
我也不知道为什么按这个顺序，无论如何
Here is my other list.
这是另一张表
I have my two lists that I have sorted.
我现在有两张已经排好序的表
So, this is A[1] to A[|n/2|] and A[|n/2|+1] to A[n]
好，这个就是A[1..n/2]，那个就是A[n/2+1..n]
for the way it will be called in this program.
这就是程序要调用的排序方式
And now to merge these two, what I want to do
要归并它们两个，我要做的是
is produce a sorted list out of both of them.
从这两者出发得到一个排好序的总表
What I do is first observe
我要做的是先观察
where is the smallest element of any two lists that are already sorted?
两张已排序的列表中，最小元素是多少？
It's in one of two places, the head of the first list or the head of the second list.
它在两个地方之一，第一张表之首或第二张表之首
I look at those two elements and say which one is smaller? This one is smaller.
我看一下这两个元素哪个更小，这个更小
Then what I do is output into my output array the smaller of the two.
然后我将这两个中较小的那个输出到最终的输出数组中
And I cross it off.
然后叉掉
And now where is the next smallest element?
下一个最小元素在哪？
And the answer is it's going to be the head of one of these two lists.
答案仍是两个列表的首元素之一
Then I cross out this guy and put him here and circle this one.
我叉掉这个家伙，放在这里，圈上这个
Now I look at these two guys.
现在我看这两个家伙
This one is smaller so I output that and circle that one.
这个更小，所以我把它输出，圈上那个
Now I look at these two guys, output 9.
现在我看这两个，输出9
So, every step here is some fixed number of operations
所以，这里的每一步都是固定数目的操作
that is independent of the size of the arrays at each step.
这和每一步中的数组尺寸无关
Each individual step is just me looking at two elements
每一步中，我只关注两个元素
and picking out the smallest and advancing some pointers into the array
并挑出最小的，再把数组指针推进一位
so that I know where the current head of that list is.
所以我总是知道当前的表头在哪
And so, therefore, the time is order n on n total elements.
是故，对于总数为n的输入，时间是θ(n)的
The time to actually go through this and merge two lists is order n.
把这两个遍历和归并的时间是θ(n)
We sometimes call this linear time
我们有时将此称为线性时间
because it's not quadratic or whatever.
因为它不是平方的或怎么样的
It is proportional to n, proportional to the input size. It's linear time.
它与n成正比，与输入规模成正比，这就是线性时间
I go through and just do this simple operation,
我在遍历时，仅仅做这些简单操作
just working up these lists,
先把这些表做出来
and in the end I have done essentially n operations,
最后我做了必须的n个操作
order n operations each of which cost constant time.
线性阶次操作，每个操作耗费常数时间
That's a total of order n time.
所以总时间是θ(n)的
Everybody with me? OK.
大家跟得上吗？好
So, this is a recursive program.
那么，这是个递归程序
We can actually now write what is called a recurrence for this program.
我们实际上可以为该程序写出一个所谓递归式
The way we do that is say let's let the time to sort n elements to be T(n).
我们这么做，比如为n个元素排序的时间是T(n)
Then how long does it take to do step one?
第一步要用多长时间？
That's just constant time.
只用了常数时间
We just check to see if n is 1, and if it is we return.
我们只是检查n是否为1，如果是则返回
That's independent of the size of anything that we are doing.
这一步与我们所做工作的输入规模毫无关系
It just takes a certain number of machine instructions
它只耗费固定数目的机器指令
on whatever machine and we say it is constant time.
无论什么机器都一样，我们只说常数时间
We call that theta one.
我们称之为θ(1)
This is actually a little bit of an abuse if you get into it.
如果你较真的话，好吧，这有点儿滥用θ符号的意思
And the reason is because typically
其原因是，典型情况下
in order to say it you need to say what it is growing with.
如果你要用这个符号你就要描述它增长时的情形
Nevertheless, we use this as an abuse of the notation just to
反正，我们这里就滥用一次这个记号表示
mean it is a constant.
“它是个常数”
So, that's an abuse just so people know.
总之，"滥用"，写在这里提醒你们
But it simplifies things if I can just write theta one.
不过写θ(1)确实可以让事情变得简单
And it basically means the same thing.
而且它想要表达的意思是一样的
Now we recursively sort these two things.
现在我们递归地对这两者排序
How can I describe that?
我怎么来描述呢？
The time to do this, I can describe recursively as
做这个的时候，我可以递归地描述成
T of ceiling of n over 2 plus T of n minus ceiling of n over 2.
T(n/2向上取整)+T(n减去n/2向上取整)
That is actually kind of messy,
这看起来好像有点儿乱
so what we will do is just be sloppy and write 2T(n/2).
所以我们就略去细节，写成2T(n/2)
So, this is just us being sloppy.
这真的是只是略去细节
And we will see on Friday in recitation that it is OK to be sloppy.
周五的复习课上，我们会看到为什么可以这样略去
That's the great thing about algorithms.
这是关于算法的大妙处
As long as you are rigorous and precise, you can be as sloppy as you want.
只要你严格而精确，你可以任意略去细节
This is sloppy because I didn't worry about what was going on,
这种略去，是因为我不担心会发生意外
because it turns out it doesn't make any difference.
因为到头来是没区别的
And we are going to actually see that that is the case.
而我们将要看到，正是如此
And, finally, I have to merge the two sorted lists which have a total of n elements.
最后，我要归并已排好序的、总元素数为n的两张表
And we just analyze that using the merge subroutine.
我们刚刚用归并子程序分析过
And that takes us to theta n time.
这耗用了我们θ(n)的时间
That allows us now to write a recurrence for the performance of merge sort.
这就使得我们现在能够为归并排序的性能写出递归表达式
Which is to say that T of n is equal to theta 1 if n equals 1
就是说，若n=1，则T(n)=θ(1)
and 2T of n over 2 plus theta of n if n is bigger than 1.
而如果n>1，则T(n)=2T(n/2)+θ(n)
Because either I am doing step one or I am doing all steps one, two and three.
因为无论我做的是第一步还是全部的三个步骤
Here I am doing step one and I return and I am done.
要么，我做第一步并返回，就做完了
Or else I am doing step one, I don't return, and then I also do steps two and three.
要么，我做第一步，没返回，接着做二三两步
So, I add those together.
然后把所有的加起来
I could say theta n plus theta 1, but theta n plus theta 1 is just theta n
我可以说结果是θ(n)+θ(1)，但θ(n)+θ(1)就是θ(n)
because theta 1 is a lower order term than theta n and I can throw it away.
因为θ(1)比θ(n)低阶，可以直接舍去
It is either theta 1 or it is 2T of n over 2 plus theta n.
它或是θ(1)或是2T(n/2)+θ(n)
Now, typically we won't be writing this.
好吧，我们通常不写这个
Usually we omit this.
通常我们省略这个
If it makes no difference to the solution of the recurrence,
它对递归解没有影响
we will usually omit constant base cases.
通常我们会省略常数的基本情形
In algorithms, it's not true generally in mathematics,
注意，在数学中一般不成立
but in algorithms if you are running something on a constant size input
但在算法中如果你给的是常数规模的输入
it takes constant time always.
那它也只需要常数的运行时间
So, we don't worry about what this value is.
所以，我们并不操心具体的是多少
And it turns out it has no real impact on the asymptotic solution of the recurrence.
而且，这对于递归的渐近解并无实际影响
How do we solve a recurrence like this?
我们怎么样解这样的递归式？
I now have T of n expressed in terms of T of n over 2.
现在我是用T(n/2)来表示T(n)的
That's in the book and it is also in Lecture 2.
这个书上有，我们在第二讲中也会讲
We are going to do Lecture 2 to solve that,
我们将在第二讲中解决这个问题
but in the meantime what I am going to do is
但现在，我将
give you a visual way of understanding what this costs,
让大家直观地理解究竟运行成本几何
which is one of the techniques we will elaborate on next time.
这种方法的具体知识下集分解
It is called a recursion tree technique.
它叫做递归树方法
And I will use it for the actual recurrence
我会在实际的递归式上应用该方法
that is almost the same 2T(n/2),
T(n)基本上等于2T(n/2)…
but I am going to actually explicitly,
后面的式子我也显式地也写出来
because I want you to see where it occurs,
因为我想让你明白这是怎么来的
plus some constant times n where c is a constant greater than zero.
后面加上某个常数，乘以n，c是大于0的常数
So, we are going to look at this recurrence with a base case of order one.
所以我们来看看这个基本情形为θ(1)的递归式
I am just making the constant in here,
我只是把常数写了出来
the upper bound on the constant be explicit rather than implicit.
用cn显式函数地替换掉了隐式的θ(n)
And the way you do a recursion tree is the following.
构造递归树的方法如下
You start out by writing down the left-hand side of the recurrence.
你先把递归式的左半部分写下来
And then what you do is you say well, that is equal to,
然后你说，好，这个等于
and now let's write it as a tree.
现在我们把它写成树状结构
I do c of n work plus now I am going to have to do work on each of my two children.
我做了cn的工作，加上我必须在子节点处做这些
If I sum up what is in here,
如果我在这里把结果加起来的话
I get this because that is what the recurrence says, T(n)=2T(n/2)+cn.
我得到这个，因为递归式说T(n)=2T(n/2)+cn
I have 2T(n/2)+cn.
我得到了2T(n/2)+cn
Then I do it again.
然后继续下去
I have cn here.
我这里有个cn
I now have here cn/2.
现在我这里有个cn/2
And here is cn/2.
这里也有cn/2
And each of these now has a T(n/4).
现在，每一项变成T(n/4)了
And these each have a T(n/4).
这些项各有T(n/4)
And this has a T(n/4).
这里得到了T(n/4)
And I keep doing that, the dangerous dot, dot, dots.
然后我一直做下去，危险的省略号
And, if I keep doing that, I end up with it looking like this.
并且，如果我一直做下去，最终就会变成这样
And I keep going down until I get to a leaf.
我一直探下去，直到到达叶节点
And a leaf, I have essentially a T(1). That is theta(1).
对于叶节点，我只有T(1)，即θ(1)
And so the first question I ask here is, what is the height of this tree?
所以我的第一个问题是，这树的高度是多少？
Yeah. It's lgn.
对，lgn
It's actually very close to exactly lgn
实际上，它精确地接近lgn
because I am starting out at the top with n
因为我是从顶点n出发的
and then I go to n/2 and n/4 and all the way down until I get to 1.
然后我n/2、n/4这样一路算下去，直到1为止
The number of halvings of n until I get to 1 is lgn
从n到1的折半次数是lgn
so the height here is lgn.
所以这里的高度也是lgn
It's OK if it is constant times lgn.
其实是lgn的常数倍
It doesn't matter.
不过不要紧
How many leaves are in this tree, by the way?
那末，顺便问下，树上有多少叶节点？
How many leaves does this tree have? Yeah.
整棵树上的叶节点数目是多少？请讲
The number of leaves, once again, is actually pretty close. It's actually n.
叶节点的数目…其实就是n
If you took it all the way down.
如果你这样一路算下来
Let's make some simplifying assumption.
我们来做一些简化的假设
n is a perfect power of 2, so it is an integer power of 2.
设n是个2的完全幂数，即2的整数次幂
Then this is exactly lgn to get down to T(1).
这样，降到T(1)时，正好有lgn步
And then there are exactly n leaves, because the number of leaves here,
是故总共有n个叶节点，因为这里的叶节点总数
the number of nodes at this level is 1, 2, 4, 8.
这一级上的节点数是1，然后是2、4、8
And if I go down height h, I have 2 to the h leaves,
如果树的高度是h，我就有2的h次方个叶节点
2 to the lgn, that is just n.
这里是2的lgn次方，这正好是n
We are doing math here, right?
我们这是做数学题呢，对吧？
Now let's figure out how much work,
现在，让我们计算一下做了多少工作
if I look at adding up everything in this tree I am going to get T(n),
看一下T(n)情况下把树中的一切加起来是多少
so let's add that up.
让我们来算一下总和
Well, let's add it up level by level.
好，让我们一级级地加和
How much do we have in the first level? Just cn.
第一级中我们用了多少时间？仅仅是cn
If I add up the second level, how much do I have? cn.
如果我把第二级的加起来有多少？cn
How about if I add up the third level? cn.
第三级怎么样？还是cn
How about if I add up all the leaves? Theta n.
那所有的叶结点加起来有多少？θ(n)
It is not necessarily cn because the boundary case may have a different constant.
它不一定就是cn，因为边界情况可能是别的常数
It is actually theta n, but cn all the way here.
它实际上是θ(n)，但在这里算下来都是cn
If I add up the total amount, that is equal to cn times lgn,
如果我计算总数，那就是cn乘以lgn
because that's the height,
因为那是树的高度
that is how many cn's I have here, plus theta n.
也是我有多少个cn，还要加上θ(n)
And this is a higher order term than this, so this goes away,
第一项比第二项高阶，所以第二项不要了
get rid of the constants, that is equal to theta(n lg n).
常数项不要了，这就等价于θ(nlgn)
And theta(n lg n) is asymptotically faster than theta(n^2).
而且考虑渐近的情况，θ(nlgn)比θ(n²)要快
So, merge sort, on a large enough input size,
因此，归并排序在一个充分大的输入规模下
is going to beat insertion sort.
将优于插入排序
Merge sort is going to be a faster algorithm.
归并排序是个更快的算法
Sorry, you guys, I didn't realize you couldn't see over there.
不好意思，我没发现你们看不到那里
You should speak up if you cannot see.
看不见的话就要说嘛
So, this is a faster algorithm
所以，这是一个更快的算法
because theta(n lg n) grows more slowly than theta(n^2).
因为θ(nlgn)的算法比θ(n²)的增长得慢
And merge sort asymptotically beats insertion sort.
所以渐近情况下，归并排序胜过插入排序
Even if you ran insertion sort on a supercomputer,
即使你在一台超级计算机上运行插入排序
somebody running on a PC with merge sort
而另一个人在PC上运行归并排序
for sufficient large input will clobber them
在输入规模充分大时也是后者会赢
because actually n^2 is way bigger than n lgn once you get the n's to be large.
因为事实上在n充分大时，n²就是比nlgn大
And, in practice, merge sort tends to win here for n bigger than, say, 30 or so.
并且实际上，在n大于，30吧，归并排序就更快了
If you have a very small input like 30 elements,
如果你有一个很小的输入，30个元素左右的规模
insertion sort is a perfectly decent sort to use.
插入排序是个完美优雅的可用排序算法
But merge sort is going to be a lot faster
但是，归并排序终将快很多
even for something that is only a few dozen elements.
即使在只有百把个元素的规模的情况下
It is going to actually be a faster algorithm.
归并排序也将成为更快的算法
That's sort of the lessons, OK?
课就上到这儿好不好？
Remember that to get your recitation assignments and attend recitation on Friday.
记得领取复习课作业，然后周五来上复习课
Because we are going to be going through a bunch of the things
因为我们还有好些事儿得做呢
And see you next Monday.
下周一见